David Nicholson

July 2024

CONTACT Email: nicholdav@gmail.com Website: nicholdav.info

GitHub: nickledave **ORCID:** 0000-0002-4261-4719

SUMMARY

Research software engineer with a background in neuroscience, cognitive science, and bioacoustics. Extensive experience in basic and applied artificial intelligence research, including several DARPA programs. Lead maintainer of a set of open source software tools for researchers studying how animals communicate with sound.

EXPERIENCE

BAE FAST Labs

Principal Scientist

January 2024-present

 Principal Investigator on Internal Research and Development grant to develop Trustworthy Artificial Intelligence approaches applied to the radio frequency signal domain

Embedded Intelligence

Machine Intelligence Engineer

2019-2023

- Planned and executed research on defences against adversarial attacks on computer vision models; Lead the design and development of novel algorithms for reverse engineering of adversarial attacks; contributed to the design and development of methods for quality assurance of machine learning models post-deployment
- Developed novel algorithms for signal restoration by applying deep learning models to the radio frequency signal domain

VocalPy

Lead maintainer

2017-present

• Developed and maintained a set of software tools for researchers studying acoustic communication, and built community around the software: vocalpy.org

Biology Department, Emory University

Postdoctoral Researcher

2017-2019

Planned and executed cognitive neuroscience research, as a member of a team developing brain-inspired algorithms for continual machine learning on the DARPA program Lifelong Learning Machines (L2M)

SELECTED
PUBLICATIONS
AND
CONFERENCE
PROCEEDINGS

Nicholson, D. A., & Cohen, Y. (2023). vak: a neural network framework for researchers studying animal acoustic communication. In *Python in Science Conference*. https://doi.org/10.25080/gerudo-f2bc6f59-008

Nicholson, D. A. (2023). Crowsetta: A Python tool to work with any format for annotating animal vocalizations and bioacoustics data. *Journal of Open Source Software*. https://joss.theoj.org/papers/10.21105/joss.05338

Nicholson, D.A., & Emanuele V. (2023). Reverse engineering adversarial attacks with fingerprints from adversarial examples. *arXiv*. doi.org/10.48550/arXiv.2301.13869

Nicholson, D.A., & Prinz A. A. (2022). Could simplified stimuli change how the brain performs visual search tasks? A deep neural network study. *Journal of Vision*. doi.org/10.1167/jov.22.7.3

Code: https://github.com/NickleDave/Nicholson-Prinz-JOV-DNNs-bio-vis

Cohen, Y., **Nicholson, D. A.**, Sanchioni, A., Mallaber, E. K., Skidanova, V., & Gardner, T. J. (2022). Automated annotation of birdsong with a neural network that segments spectrograms. *Elife*.

https://doi.org/10.7554/eLife.63853

Code: https://github.com/yardencsGitHub/tweetynet

Nicholson, D.A. (2016). A Comparison of Machine Learning Algorithms Applied to Birdsong Elements. *Proceedings of the 15th Python in Science Conference*.

https://doi.org/10.25080/Majora-629e541a-008

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Programming language experience and software engineering skills

- Python (2015-present): Expert in frameworks for machine learning (scikit-learn) and deep learning (torch, tensorflow); Expert in core data science stack (numpy, scipy, pandas) and data visualization (matplotlib, seaborn); Expert in unit testing frameworks (unittest, pytest)
- git (2015-present): Expert, use daily for version control
- Forges (2015-present): Expert in using forges (GitHub, BitBucket) to develop and contribute to software: use daily for branch-based workflows; continuous integration (e.g., Travis CI, GitHub Actions)
- Bash, UNIX environment (2016–): Use daily. Proficient with command-line scripts for reproducible data processing and analysis pipelines.
- Make (2018–present): Proficient with Makefiles for reproducible analyses and for running development tasks
- Docker (2019–present): Familiar with containerization and delivery of Python code in Docker images
- Amazon Web Services (2019-present): Proficient with EC2; Familiar with S3 storage
- LATEX (2018 present): Proficient, use routinely for publications
- MATLAB (2012–present): Familiar with MATLAB-based applications of science and engineering methods

ORGANIZING

The United States Research Software Engineer Association

Virtual, USA (2022–present)

• Co-Chair of Group Management Working Group (2022-present)

Scientific Computing with Python Conference (SciPy)

Austin, Texas, USA (2020–present)

- Communications chair (2020-2022)
- Hybrid chair (2023–)

pyOpenSci

Virtual, USA (2018–present)

- Reviewer, Editor (2018-present)
- Editor-in-Chief (2022-February 2024)

Data Science for Scientists ATL

Graduate data science group. Atlanta, GA, USA

(2017-2022)

• Helped found group and obtain charter from Laney Graduate Student Government; Planned events, coordinated monthly meetings

EDUCATION

Ph.D. Neuroscience

2017

Emory University, Atlanta, GA

Advisor: Samuel J. Sober

B.Sc. Biology 2010

University of South Florida, Tampa, Florida

Summa cum laude. Minor: Spanish linguistics.